<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About this Website</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2023-09-06</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="contents-and-strucutre-webseite" n="2">
                <head>Contents and Structure of the Website</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>This online portal is designed as a user-friendly, web-based resource with
                    extensive search options. It uses a diverse range of texts, primary sources, and
                    videos to convey content related to the history of German-speaking Jews outside
                    the German-speaking regions of Europe. The different formats enable visitors to
                    delve into the subjects at multiple levels of detail. The website as a whole has
                    a modular structure, allowing visitors and readers to navigate from the general
                    introduction to the individual country sections.</p>
                <p>Our portal is an expanding work in progress and has been launched with a
                    preliminary selection of articles. To date, we have commissioned more than
                    thirty individual country studies, some of which cover locations such as
                    Curaçao, Sri Lanka, and Suriname that have not previously been investigated in
                    the context of German-Jewish history. These places were often embedded in
                    colonial structures, and these investigations therefore shed light on how Jewish
                    individuals evaluated such structures in light of their own experiences of
                    discrimination and persecution. The case studies – both primary sources and
                    biographical portraits – should be read as key documents, through which we
                    spotlight themes and aspects of the German(-speaking) Jewish Diaspora. For
                    further background, additional texts on historical figures and primary sources
                    are also being prepared and will be added on an ongoing basis.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="zielgruppe" n="2">
                <head>Target Audience</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The Diaspora portal is intended for university students, researchers, and
                    educators, as well as for school classes, interested laypeople, and, of course,
                    the descendants of the German-speaking Jews in question. In keeping with the
                    transnational nature of the German-Jewish Diaspora, the platform is multilingual
                    – currently in German and English. To reach as many users as possible, there are
                    plans to expand the website to Hebrew and Spanish. Many descendants – especially
                    those in South America – can no longer understand German, yet have grown up with
                    narrative traces of their parents’, grandparents’, or great-grandparents’ pasts.
                    We also want this website to give them access to their ancestors’ history.
                    Moreover, they are invited to contribute in their own voices via the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Bring Your Own Story</hi> section. </p>
                <p> In this way, we will extend the reach beyond a regional and national audience,
                    making full use of the cross-border opportunities posed by digital formats.</p>
                <p> The Diaspora portal addresses not only an academic readership but also a wider
                    public. Alongside an encyclopedic wealth of facts and detail, it offers clear
                    explanations of complex historical contexts, reflects on overarching questions
                    and key issues, and connects facts with analysis. </p>
                <p> It is particularly well suited for use in schools, where students can explore
                    the complex historical, social, and political reasons for the emergence of a
                    German(-speaking) Jewish Diaspora through individual life stories. At the same
                    time, the project fosters an understanding of the existential challenges of
                    leaving one’s birthplace behind and starting life afresh.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="textual-genres" n="2">
                <head>Textual Genres</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The Diaspora portal consists of <hi rendition="#b">three categories of
                        texts</hi>, conceived as ‘layers,’ and one special section, all
                    cross-referenced and interconnected through links. </p>
                <p> The first category, <hi rendition="#b">Geographical Overviews</hi>, provides the
                    longest articles, offering the historical context necessary to understand the
                    case studies </p>
                <p> The second category comprises <hi rendition="#b">Biographies</hi> of
                    German-speaking Jewish émigrés. The third category consists of <hi
                        rendition="#b">Sources</hi> that serve as key documents of German-Jewish
                    Diaspora history and are presented alongside analysis. </p>
                <p> In a special section, <hi rendition="#i"><hi rendition="#b">Bring Your Own
                            Story</hi></hi>, allows individuals to contribute unique objects
                    connected to their personal histories.</p>
                <div xml:id="geographical-overviews" n="3">
                    <head>Geographical Overviews</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p> The geographical overviews examine various countries where German-speaking
                        Jews resided, either while in transit or as long-term destinations. As
                        reference guides, they outline developments and key themes, combining
                        factual information with analytical insights into the German-Jewish Diaspora
                        as it took shape in the context of each country. They follow a consistent
                        thematic structure, highlighting relevant national circumstances before and
                        after 1933 that are relevant to Jewish history.</p>
                    <p> Their length varies by country or region and reflects various types of
                        diasporic lifeworlds – from centers of German-speaking Jewish life to
                        transit countries that only hosted temporary local communities of
                        German(-speaking) Jews. The format focuses on thematic focus areas, thus
                        considering several topics on a recurring basis to create a consistent
                        textual structure and facilitate comparisons between individual countries.
                        The project does not limit its portrayal of the highly diverse German-Jewish
                        Diaspora to the national level, but also considers individual cities,
                        neighborhoods, and peripheral areas. This also makes it possible to showcase
                        the history of German-speaking Jews’ day-to-day local experiences.</p>
                    <p> Recurring thematic categories in the geographical overviews include: </p>
                    <p>1. <hi rendition="#b">Everyday Life</hi> | 2. <hi rendition="#b"
                            >Institutions</hi> | 3. <hi rendition="#b">Identity and Religiosity
                        </hi> | 4. <hi rendition="#b">Gender and Generations</hi> | 5. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Transnational Networks</hi> | 6. <hi rendition="#b"
                            >Language</hi> | 7. <hi rendition="#b">Encounters</hi> | 8. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Cultural and Knowledge Transfer</hi> | 9. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Return</hi> | 10. <hi rendition="#b">Legacy and
                            Memory.</hi></p>
                    <p> The ten thematic categories and their defined subcategories are not intended
                        as strict templates to be addressed for every region. Instead, the assigned
                        authors have independently selected the themes relevant to a given country
                        and addressed them in their overviews. </p>
                    <p> However, certain topics have been covered as consistently as possible across
                        all studies, in particular the institutionalization of the German-Jewish
                        Diaspora through clubs or periodicals; the everyday challenges community
                        members faced; and encounters with other minority groups and mainstream
                        society. In addition, the texts address the significance of memory and
                        nostalgia for constructing a shared ‘diasporic identity’ as well as
                        transnational networks extending beyond the country in question – including
                        ongoing ties to the Old Country. These key thematic areas make it possible
                        to identify parallels and differences in a geographic cross-section. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="biographies" n="3">
                    <head>Biographies</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p> In addition to exploring the various destinations, the portal portrays
                        individuals who left the German-speaking world. Through individual and group
                        biographies, the German-Jewish Diaspora is given a human face, countering
                        the depersonalization of migration discourse. Familiarity or renown is not
                        the basis for inclusion. Alongside ‘famous’ historical figures, we also
                        consider less familiar life stories to illuminate particular aspects of the
                        German-speaking Jewish Diaspora in all their breadth. </p>
                    <p> These biographies expand the overall scope of the geographical overviews
                        through individual examples. They center on life in the Diaspora, but also
                        include many references to dreams of return to the country of origin, which
                        were occasionally fulfilled. These case studies particularly make clear how
                        hybrid, fragmented affiliations developed and changed over the course of a
                        person’s life. The thematic categories of the geographical overviews are
                        also reflected in the short biographies. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="source-interpretations" n="3">
                    <head>Source Interpretations</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p> The Diaspora portal incorporates sources – textual, visual, audio, or
                        audiovisual documents, including photographs of three-dimensional objects –
                        to ‘drill down’ into the specifics. These sources shed light on individual
                        periods of a person’s life as well as thematic areas. Each source (or group
                        of related sources) is accompanied by a description and interpretation that
                        situates it in its historical and functional context. The ‘source
                        interpretation’ rubric includes transcription and translation, as well as a
                        digital facsimile. As with the biographies, the source interpretations are
                        linked to the thematic categories used in the geographical overviews. </p>
                    <p> The sources have been located in a variety of places: public archives,
                        libraries, and museums, as well as private collections and estates. In some
                        cases, only excerpts of a source are shown, but then always along with
                        instructions on how to access the full document and a hyperlink when
                        technically feasible. </p>
                    <p> The source selection is inspired by the concept of ‘key documents’ developed
                        by Miriam Rürup, Anna Menny, and Daniel Burckhardt for the <ref
                            target="https://keydocuments.net/">Key Documents of German-Jewish
                            History</ref> project. </p>
                    <p> Key documents are defined as sources that provide exemplary insights into
                        historical developments and events – serving as entry points into larger
                        stories. This source-based layer is a centerpiece of the website. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="bring-your-own-story" n="3">
                    <head><hi rendition="#i">Bring Your Own Story</hi></head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p> Alongside traditional articles, the online portal invites contributions from
                        individuals with personal connections to Diaspora history. The <hi
                            rendition="#i">Bring Your Own Story</hi> section aims to make
                        individuals’ life trajectories in the Diaspora tangible using ‘storytelling
                        objects.’ These include everyday items, letters, photographs, or postcards,
                        as well as applied art or distinctive fabric items. Such objects link
                        personal experiences to the broader history of the German-Jewish Diaspora.
                        As distinctive vessels of memory – often reflecting multiple migration
                        experiences within a single family – they hold deep, intergenerational
                        significance. In short personal videos (of 10–15 minutes each), participants
                        reflect on their own migration stories and the role of the German-Jewish
                        Diaspora in their family histories.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--
            <div xml:id="navigation" n="2">
                <head>Navigation</head><lb/>
                <p>Das Diaspora-Portal bietet vielfältige Zugänge zu einzelnen Ländern, historischen
                    Personen, und Quellen. Die Biografien und Quellenpräsentationen sind dabei über drei
                    Reiter mit den Titeln <hi rendition="#i">Zeitstrahl</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">Karte</hi>
                    und <hi rendition="#i">Themen</hi> ansteuerbar. Alle Quellen sind über die Metadaten mit
                    einem Primärdatum versehen. Dies ist in der Regel der feststellbare Entstehungszeitpunkt
                    der Quelle. Bei lebensgeschichtlichen Interviews und Lebenserinnerungen hat sich die
                    Redaktion dafür entschieden, zwei Daten zu vergeben – den Zeitpunkt des Verfassens der
                    Quelle sowie den feststellbar historisch behandelten Zeitpunkt. Anhand dieser Daten sind
                    sie auf einem Zeitstrahl angeordnet.</p>
                <p>Neben einem Primärdatum, das den feststellbaren Entstehungszeitpunkt etwa einer Quelle
                    angibt, sind sie mit einem Primärort ausgezeichnet, der ihre Anordnung innerhalb einer
                    Karte ermöglicht. Die Kartengrundlage ist dabei bewusst keine historische, sondern eine
                    abstrahierte Karte, die in erster Linie der räumlichen Orientierung dienen soll.</p>
                <p>Der dritte Zugang erfolgt schließlich über unsere zehn Themenkategorien, durch die sich
                    die Biografien und Quellenpräsentationen thematisch verorten lassen. Über Schlagworte
                    können Besucher:innen des Portals gezielt nach für sie interessanten Personen und Quellen
                    suchen.</p>
            </div>
            -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
