<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Editorial Model and Guidelines</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2025-05-05</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="redaktionsmodell" n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Editorial Model</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The Diaspora portal is a collaborative international and interdisciplinary
                    effort. While editorial oversight and technical development are based at the
                    Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies (MMZ) in Potsdam, the
                    project is shaped by the initiative of over a hundred authors from more than
                    twenty countries who are contributing their writing in the different categories.
                    The authors of case studies include not only scholars, but also journalists and
                    professional writers. For the long term, the Diaspora platform is envisioned as
                    a platform for international, interdisciplinary, and collaborative exchange.
                    Visualized metaphorically as a ‘tree of the Diaspora,’ it aims to bring together
                    institutions of memory in countries where émigrés lived, making their work and
                    their holdings visible and strategically connecting them. </p>
                <p> Authors of the geographical overviews work together with the editorial team to
                    review biographies and source interpretations within their country or region.
                    These collaborative editorial processes were discussed during several digital
                    preliminary meetings, which also served as networking opportunities. </p>
                <p> In some cases, on top of these two stages of editorial oversight, additional
                    peer reviewers with relevant expertise checked individual essays. This
                    multi-stage review process and the close collaboration between editors and
                    authors ensure the scholarly quality of all content. </p>
                <p> The MMZ editorial team coordinates the project, but also reviews legal aspects
                    of publication and oversees all workflows. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="editorial-guidelines" n="2">
                <head>Editorial Guidelines</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> All text categories in this online portal follow a consistent structure. A short
                    summary at the beginning highlights key aspects of the country, person, or
                    source in relation to the German-Jewish Diaspora. The names of people,
                    institutions, and places are linked to standardized datasets, creating an
                    internal index and connecting the portal to other digital projects. Metadata is
                    compiled for all sources. For sources represented as digital facsimiles, the
                    online portal includes both transcriptions and translations (for texts in other
                    languages). This makes handwritten documents more legible and also allows users
                    to search the text of a source for keywords. </p>
                <p> Metadata has also been compiled for the XML transcriptions in the online
                    version, and all historical documents are annotated with metadata. </p>
                <p><!--Zur Erklärung von möglicherweise unbekannten Begriffen oder erwähnten Organisationen
                    entsteht zukünftig ein fortlaufend ergänztes Glossar.--> Also,
                    each article concludes with a short selected bibliography and links to further
                    digital resources, such as articles, online exhibitions, digitized documents,
                    podcasts, and films. </p>
                <p> Transcripts have been prepared by the editorial team as faithfully as possible,
                    largely preserving original punctuation and spelling. However, spelling mistakes
                    and abbreviations are annotated for clarity, noting any uncertainties. Emphases
                    and crossed-out text are preserved, especially when relevant to the content. </p>
                <p> The geographical overviews, biographies, and source interpretations are originally
                    written in either German or English. Contributions composed in English retain
                    the spelling conventions of their respective authors (either US or
                    UK/Commonwealth English). </p>
                <p> The interface and content of the online portal are designed to be fully
                    bilingual (German and English). Any missing translations are currently in
                    progress and will be added on a rolling basis. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
