<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About this Website</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2023-09-06</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="contents-and-strucutre-webseite" n="2">
                <head>Contents and Structure of the Website</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>With the Diaspora Portal, we aim to provide a user-friendly online resource with
                    comprehensive search capabilities. Content on German-Jewish history outside the
                    German-speaking world will be presented through various text levels, source
                    types, and video content. The different forms of presentation allow for
                    different degrees of specialization. The entire portal has a modular structure,
                    so that visitors can click and "read" their way from the introduction to the
                    overall topic through the different countries.</p>
                <p>Our portal is constantly being expanded and will start with a limited preview. So
                    far, more than 30 overview texts on individual countries have been acquired,
                    including places largely unknown to German-Jewish history such as Curaçao, Sri
                    Lanka and Suriname. These places were often integrated into colonial structures
                    and at the same time provide an insight into how colonial structures were
                    perceived by Jews in the context of their own experiences of discrimination and
                    persecution. The case studies - sources as well as biographical portraits - are
                    to be understood here as key documents with which we shine a thematic spotlight
                    on central aspects of the German(-speaking) Jewish diaspora. In the background,
                    additional texts on historical figures and sources are in preparation and will
                    be added on an ongoing basis.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="zielgruppe" n="2">
                <head>Target Audience</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The online source portal is aimed primarily at university students, teachers and
                    scholars in the field of Jewish history, but also at high school students and
                    interested members of the general public, and, last but not least, the
                    descendants of the German-speaking Jews who are the focus of attention here. In
                    keeping with the theme of a German-Jewish diaspora and its transnational
                    networks, it is currently bilingual - in German and English. In order to reach
                    as many visitors as possible, the portal will also be available in Hebrew and
                    Spanish in the future. Especially the descendants - many of them from South
                    America - often do not have access to the German language, but have grown up
                    with the stories of their parents, grandparents and great-grandparents. With
                    this portal we would like to give them access to the history of their ancestors.
                    As experts on their own family history, they can also have their say through the
                        <hi rendition="#i">Bring Your Own Story</hi> section. </p>
                <p>In this way, we expand our user group beyond the regional and national target
                    audience and make the best possible use of the transnational possibilities of
                    online offerings.</p>
                <p>With the Diaspora Portal, we are addressing a broader public beyond the academic
                    specialist audience. In addition to an encyclopedic density of figures and
                    details, complex interrelationships and backgrounds are conveyed in a
                    comprehensible manner, overarching questions and central aspects are reflected
                    upon, and factual information is combined with analytical interpretations.</p>
                <p>The Diaspora Portal is particularly suitable for teaching in schools. On the one
                    hand, the complex historical, social and political reasons that led to the
                    emergence of a German(-speaking) Jewish diaspora can be discovered by students on
                    the basis of individual fates. At the same time, a historical understanding of
                    the existential difficulties and challenges of losing one's homeland and
                    starting anew is made possible.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="textual-genres" n="2">
                <head>Textual Genres</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The diaspora portal is made up of a total of <hi rendition="#b">three levels of
                        text</hi> and a special section, which are linked to each other by
                    cross-references in the form of links. </p>
                <p> The first genre is the so-called <hi rendition="#b">Geographical Overview</hi>. These
                    articles form the longest contributions and are intended to provide the necessary
                    historical context in order to better situate the case studies. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Biographies</hi> of German-speaking Jews in emigration
                    represent a second level. The third level consists of <hi rendition="#b"
                        >Sources</hi> that can be regarded as key documents for a history of the
                    German-Jewish diaspora and are presented together with accompanying
                    interpretations. </p>
                <p>In a special section – <hi rendition="#i"><hi rendition="#b">Bring Your Own
                            Story</hi></hi> – singular objects can be connected with a personal
                    story.</p>
                <div xml:id="geographical-overviews" n="3">
                    <head>Geographical Overviews</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The geographical overview articles on various transit and destination countries of
                        German-speaking Jews serve as introductions and are intended to identify
                        research questions. As in a handbook, lines of development and core aspects
                        are presented. Factual information is combined with an analytical
                        interpretation of the German-Jewish diaspora that may have developed in each
                        country. The country studies are structured as consistently as possible
                        according to different thematic areas and identify the relevant national
                        circumstances for Jewish history before and after 1933.</p>
                    <p>The scope of the geographical overviews varies from country to country,
                        presenting different variants of diasporic lifeworlds - from centres of a
                        German-speaking diaspora to transit countries with only a temporary
                        German-speaking Jewish presence. The geographical overviews are based on thematic
                        focus categories. Therefore, they deal with several recurring themes in
                        order to create a coherent text structure and to allow for comparisons
                        between the individual countries. The extremely diverse German-Jewish
                        diaspora is to be presented not only on a national level, but also in
                        individual cities or neighbourhoods as well as in the periphery. In this
                        way, the history of the experiences of German-speaking Jews can be revealed
                        on a local level.</p>
                    <p>Possible topics along which the geographical overviews can be read are:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rendition="#b">Everyday Life</hi> | 2. <hi rendition="#b"
                            >Institutions</hi> | 3. <hi rendition="#b">Identity and Religiosity
                        </hi> | 4. <hi rendition="#b">Gender and Generation</hi> | 5. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Transnational Networks</hi> | 6. <hi rendition="#b"
                            >Language</hi> | 7. <hi rendition="#b">Encounters</hi> | 8. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Cultural and Knowledge Transfer</hi> | 9. <hi
                            rendition="#b">Return</hi> | 10. <hi rendition="#b">Heritage and
                            Remembrance.</hi></p>
                    <p>With their specific subcategories, the ten thematic categories do not serve
                        as a strict guideline for each geographical overview. Instead, the authors
                        responsible have individually identified the topics relevant to each country
                        and discussed them in their overview texts.</p>
                    <p>However, what was dealt with as recurrently as possible in all country
                        studies was the respective institutionalization of the German-Jewish
                        diaspora, for example through corresponding associations or magazines, the
                        challenges to be overcome in everyday life and the encounters with other
                        minority groups and the majority society. In addition, the importance of
                        memory and nostalgia for the construction of a common 'diaspora identity' as
                        well as the transnational networks that extend beyond the respective
                        country, including links back to the former homeland. Parallels and
                        differences can be identified in the geographical longitudinal section
                        through these relevant topics.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="biographies" n="3">
                    <head>Biographies</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>In addition to the various destinations, historical actors who left the
                        German-speaking world are portrayed. Individual or group biographies are
                        intended to give the German-Jewish diaspora a face, so to speak, and to
                        counteract the depersonalization associated with the subject of migration.
                        It is not important whether the person is known. In addition to 'prominent'
                        historical figures, we also take a look at previously unknown biographies if
                        they shed light on particular aspects of the German-speaking Jewish diaspora
                        in all its diversity.</p>
                    <p>The biographies delve deeper into the overall context of the respective
                        geographical overview articles using individual examples. The focus is on life in the
                        diaspora. There are also many references to a hoped-for, temporary or actual
                        return to the country of origin. It is precisely through such case studies
                        that it becomes clear how the hybrid, often fragmented belongings of those
                        affected emerged and also changed over the course of their lives. In the
                        short biographies, the thematic focal points of the geographical overview articles recur
                        and can be illuminated by way of example.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="source-interpretations" n="3">
                    <head>Source Interpretations</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Sources that we incorporate into the Diaspora Portal as text, image, sound or
                        audiovisual documents - including images of three-dimensional objects - are
                        used to conduct in-depth explorations. They shed light on individual periods
                        of life and subject areas. Each source (or a coherent set of sources) is
                        described and interpreted in order to place it in its context of origin and
                        use. In addition to a transcription and translation, the source
                        interpretation includes a digital facsimile. As in the biographies, the
                        sources and interpretation texts are also intended to deepen the thematic
                        categories of the geographical overviews using specific examples.</p>
                    <p>The origin of the sources varies: they come from public archives, libraries
                        or museums as well as from private collections and estates. In some cases,
                        we only show excerpts from a source - but then always with a reference to
                        the accessibility of the entire document and (where technically possible)
                        with a corresponding link to a complete version.</p>
                    <p> In selecting the sources, we were guided by the idea of so-called key
                        documents, as developed by Miriam Rürup together with Anna Menny and Daniel
                        Burckhardt in the context of the <ref target="https://keydocuments.net">Key
                            Documents of German-Jewish History</ref>. </p>
                    <p>The term key documents describes selected sources which are used as examples
                        to provide insight into historical contexts and events. - as a kind of 'door
                        opener'. This source-based text level forms a central element of the
                        website.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="bring-your-own-story" n="3">
                    <head><hi rendition="#i">Bring Your Own Story</hi></head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p> In addition to conventional texts, we want to gradually give people who are
                        themselves part of this history a voice. The section '<hi rendition="#i"
                            >Bring Your Own Story</hi>' section aims to make their lives in the
                        diaspora tangible by means of individual storytelling objects. They include
                        everyday objects, letters, photos or maps, but also applied art or special
                        textile objects. The various objects combine personal experiences with the
                        history of the German-Jewish diaspora. As unique carriers of memory, which
                        often reflect multiple migration experiences within a family, they have
                        deep, cross-generational meanings. In 10 to 15-minute personal videos, our
                        interviewees reflect on their own migration biography and the role of the
                        German-Jewish diaspora in their family history.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--
            <div xml:id="navigation" n="2">
                <head>Navigation</head><lb/>
                <p>Das Diaspora-Portal bietet vielfältige Zugänge zu einzelnen Ländern, historischen
                    Personen, und Quellen. Die Biografien und Quellenpräsentationen sind dabei über drei
                    Reiter mit den Titeln <hi rendition="#i">Zeitstrahl</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">Karte</hi>
                    und <hi rendition="#i">Themen</hi> ansteuerbar. Alle Quellen sind über die Metadaten mit
                    einem Primärdatum versehen. Dies ist in der Regel der feststellbare Entstehungszeitpunkt
                    der Quelle. Bei lebensgeschichtlichen Interviews und Lebenserinnerungen hat sich die
                    Redaktion dafür entschieden, zwei Daten zu vergeben – den Zeitpunkt des Verfassens der
                    Quelle sowie den feststellbar historisch behandelten Zeitpunkt. Anhand dieser Daten sind
                    sie auf einem Zeitstrahl angeordnet.</p>
                <p>Neben einem Primärdatum, das den feststellbaren Entstehungszeitpunkt etwa einer Quelle
                    angibt, sind sie mit einem Primärort ausgezeichnet, der ihre Anordnung innerhalb einer
                    Karte ermöglicht. Die Kartengrundlage ist dabei bewusst keine historische, sondern eine
                    abstrahierte Karte, die in erster Linie der räumlichen Orientierung dienen soll.</p>
                <p>Der dritte Zugang erfolgt schließlich über unsere zehn Themenkategorien, durch die sich
                    die Biografien und Quellenpräsentationen thematisch verorten lassen. Über Schlagworte
                    können Besucher:innen des Portals gezielt nach für sie interessanten Personen und Quellen
                    suchen.</p>
            </div>
            -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
