<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About this Publication Project</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                        European-Jewish Studies</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2023-09-20</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Research Project</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The most important centers of a German-Jewish diaspora are well researched,
                    particularly during the Nazi Period, as individual places and partly also in
                    their development over a longer period of time. However, an overview of the
                    German-Jewish diaspora on a transnational basis that considers earlier and later
                    periods of German-Jewish migration does not yet exist. The publication project
                    “History of the German-Jewish Diaspora” aims to close this gap. Based on the
                    latest research it seeks to present <hi rendition="#g">for the first time an
                        overall history</hi> that takes a closer look at the various historical
                    phases of a German-Jewish diaspora with its wide range of destinations. </p>
                <p> In pursuit of this objective, the <hi rendition="#g">hybrid publication
                        project</hi> “History of the German-Jewish Diaspora” commenced in 2023. As a
                    research project of the Academic Working Group of the Leo Baeck Institute in
                    Germany (WAG) it is located at the Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish
                    Studies in Potsdam under its Director Prof. Dr. Miriam Rürup. The project is
                    designed on two different, complementary publication levels: on the one hand, it
                    envisions a volume on the history of the German-Jewish diaspora, and on the
                    other, an online source portal. </p>

                <p> The planned <hi rendition="#g">print publication</hi> is intended as a
                    continuation of the LBI's renowned and successful series of overviews, which
                    were published in five volumes so far between 1996 and 2012 (<hi rendition="#i"
                        >German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi>, C. H. Beck Munich). While the
                    previous volumes dealt with Jewish life within the German states, the aim now is
                    to present a standard work on German-Jewish history <hi rendition="#g"
                        >outside</hi> and <hi rendition="#g">beyond</hi> the German-speaking lands.
                    To this end, the migration movements of jews who belonged to the German
                    linguistic and cultural area and who had to leave it in large numbers,
                    especially in the course of the 1930s, will be examined. </p>

                <p> In addition to the volume, a <hi rendition="#g">digital source portal</hi> will
                    be launched. It seeks to make an interested public aware of further, less
                    well-known sites of German-Jewish emigration and exile. The portal’s focus lies on
                    the fates and lives of Jews, who from the 1840s onwards built up a new existence
                    permanently or temporarily in around 90 (transit) countries countries - from A
                    for Argentina to Z for <hi rendition="#i">Zypern</hi>. The German-Jewish diaspora is to be made
                    visible via the website as a transnational network that was characterized by
                    dynamic relationships beyond individual places of immigration as well as by
                    return and remigration. <hi rendition="#g">(Interactive) maps</hi> should play a
                    central role in illustrating the diversity of this diaspora over the course of
                    history and the individual migratory movements of German-speaking Jews. </p>

                <p> The hybrid research project, whose digital content goes beyond a conventional
                    “thinking in printed pages”, ultimately aims to create <hi rendition="#g"
                        >synergies</hi>. Thus, both forms of publication will complement each other
                    in addressing the temporally broad topic of a German-Jewish diaspora. QR codes
                    placed in the volume are, for example, intended to act as a link by allowing
                    access to the digital portal. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Target Audience</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The online source portal is primarily aimed at university students, teachers
                    and scholars in the field of Jewish history, but also at high school students
                    and interested members of the general public. In keeping with the subject of a
                    German-Jewish diaspora and its transnational ties, the website is planned to be
                    multilingual. Its content will be available in German and English, ideally also
                    in Spanish. In order to reach as many users as possible, an inclusive web design
                    will also increase the usability and accessibility. </p>
                <p> Moreover, the portal is intended as a space for networking. How German-Jewish
                    cultural heritage is remembered and preserved today in various countries is to
                    be illustrated by means of an institutional overview. Such a directory -
                    figuratively imagined as a “<hi rendition="#g">diaspora tree</hi>” - includes
                    archives, libraries, research institutions and museums dedicated to the topic in
                    their respective national contexts. With its many ramifications, the tree is
                    intended to create a virtual network with which knowledge of archival and
                    collection holdings can be bundled and through which further research on the
                    history of the German-Jewish diaspora can be initiated. </p>
                <p>In addition to historical reconstruction, research and learning are to be linked
                    in a growing digital learning space. With its interactive maps, the presentation
                    of individual biographies and institutional forms of the German-Jewish diaspora,
                    the online portal will also be well-suited for <hi rendition="#g">school lessons
                    </hi> and <hi rendition="#g">extracurricular education</hi>. Above all, the life
                    paths of individuals offer a more personal insight into the various historical,
                    social and political reasons for emigration and exile. Against this background,
                    it is planned to include the digital source portal in the educational work of
                    the Moses Mendelssohn Center. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Editorial Model</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The digital source portal “History of the German-Jewish Diaspora” is a <hi
                        rendition="#g">joint project </hi> and collaborative effort. The Moses
                    Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies is responsible for the editorial
                    supervision and coordination, as well as the technical implementation. However,
                    the project is significantly shaped by several editors and authors, whose text
                    contributions continuously enrich the portal. </p>
                <p> For the source portal, a total of <hi rendition="#g">three text levels</hi> are
                    planned, which are related to each other through targeted cross-links: </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Firstly</hi> <hi rendition="#g">introductory texts</hi> dedicated to the respective regions of German-Jewish immigration (e.g. Europe, Latin America). Further <hi rendition="#g">survey  texts</hi> on single countries of a region form the second strand, which takes into account the different national developments in detail. In addition, individual cities or communities will be examined in order to address the development of the German-Jewish diaspora not only at the national level, but also at the local level. <lb/>
                    The third strand of this textual level, in addition to destinations, is finally formed by historical actors. They are to be given space in <hi rendition="#g">individual</hi> and  <hi rendition="#g">group biographies</hi>. The individual life stories of those affected by emigration and exile thus come to the fore, giving the German-Jewish diaspora a face, so to speak. This biographical approach is intended to counteract a “depersonalization” of the migration topic, which is currently proving to be dominant in the media of the Global North.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Secondly</hi> <hi rendition="#g">sources</hi> will be used for <hi rendition="#g">in-depth research</hi> which as text, image, sound or audiovisual documents will illuminate individual thematic fields in an exemplary manner. Three-dimensional objects are expressly welcome. In accordance with the editorial principles for an accessible reproduction of historical sources, this heterogeneous material is textually prepared by a <hi rendition="#g"
                        >source description</hi>. It will be supplemented by a transcription and a digital facsimile. </p>
                <p> <hi rendition="#i">Thirdly</hi>, an <hi rendition="#g"
                    >interpretive text</hi> will situate the source in its context of origin and use, leaving alternative interpretive possibilities and open questions to be considered.</p>
                <p>
                    The <hi rendition="#g">editors</hi> write the survey texts on single regions and suggest historical actors and sources for their subject area. Together with the editors, they solicit texts for this purpose. All submitted contributions (introductory texts, source descriptions and interpretations) undergo at least a two-stage review process: First, the project editors review the texts; in a second step, the respective editors review them.
                </p>
                <p> The survey texts are also first reviewed by the editorial team, then by all other editors. The revised texts are then reviewed again by the editors before being checked for formal guidelines and proofread. </p>
                <p> The <hi rendition="#g">authors</hi> write the introductory texts on countries, cities and municipalities, as well as the historical actors. They also write the source descriptions and interpretations. The discussion of this content will take place in specially organized workshops.</p>
                <p> This <hi rendition="#g">multi-stage review process</hi> and the close cooperation between the editorial staff, editors and authors ensure the high scholarly quality of all contributions. In addition to reviewing and editing, the editorial team is responsible for coordinating the translations as well as the procurement and subsequent transcription and markup of the sources. The translations also undergo a review process and proofreading.
                    
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
