<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About us</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                        European-Jewish Studies</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2025-05-08</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p> The online portal <hi rendition="#i">[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora</hi>
                is published by the Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies (MMZ) in
                Potsdam and maintained by the center’s project team. The website forms part of the
                MMZ’s collaborative platform on European-Jewish history, <ref
                    target="https://portal.jewish-history-online.net/">Jewish History online</ref>,
                and complements the forthcoming volume from the Leo Baeck Institute in the book
                series <hi rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi> (scheduled for
                publication in early 2027).<lb/>
            </p>
            <div xml:id="team-portal" n="2">
                <head>Portal Team</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Daniel Burckhardt, M.A. (Technical Implementation)</hi>
                    <lb/> has been a research associate at the Moses Mendelssohn Center since 2021,
                    where he is responsible for the technical development of all digital projects.
                    He previously oversaw the technical aspects of the <hi rendition="#i">Key
                        Documents of German-Jewish History</hi> at the Institute for the History of
                    German Jews (IGdJ). He studied in Zurich and Berlin and held posts as a
                    researcher at ETH Zurich, Humboldt University, the Leibniz Centre for
                    Contemporary History Potsdam, and the German Historical Institute in Washington,
                    D.C. He is also a member of the editorial board and steering committee of
                    H-Soz-Kult.<lb/></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Dr. Lisa Sophie Gebhard (Coordination and Editor)</hi>
                    <lb/> is a historian and research associate at the Moses Mendelssohn Center,
                    where she coordinates the international publication project <hi rendition="#i"
                        >[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora.</hi> She studied at institutions
                    in Berlin, Jerusalem, Kiel, and Milan, and earned her doctorate at Freie
                    Universität Berlin in 2022. Her research interests include the history of
                    Zionism, on which she co-edited the volume <hi rendition="#i">Deutschsprachige
                        Zionismen: Verfechter, Kritiker und Gegner, Organisationen und Medien
                        (1890–1938)</hi> together with David Hamann (Peter Lang, 2019). Her
                    dissertation was recently published under the title <hi rendition="#i">Davis
                        Trietsch – Der vergessene Visionär: Zukunftsentwürfe zwischen Deutschland,
                        Palästina und den USA</hi> (Mohr Siebeck, 2022) and presented at the 2023
                    Leipzig Book Fair. She lives in Berlin with her family. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Verena Kurz, M.A. (Editor)</hi>
                    <lb/> has served as external research assistant in the publication project <hi
                        rendition="#i">[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora</hi> at the Moses
                    Mendelssohn Center since 2024. She studied cultural studies, Spanish philology,
                    and Latin American studies at universities in Potsdam and Berlin and has
                    received DAAD fellowships for study and research in Argentina, Bolivia, and
                    Spain. In Buenos Aires, she ran the University of Potsdam’s Liaison Office and
                    worked at a historical archive documenting the antifascist origin story of the
                    Pestalozzi School. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Paul-Levi Mydlach (Editorial Assistant)</hi>
                    <lb/> is a student assistant at the Moses Mendelssohn Center. He studies history
                    and German studies at the University of Potsdam, focusing on German-Jewish
                    history and literature. <lb/>
                </p>

                <p><hi rendition="#b">Prof. Miriam Rürup (Project Leader)</hi>
                    <lb/> has served as the director of the Moses Mendelssohn Center since 2020. As
                    chair of the Academic Working Group of the Leo Baeck Institute, she supervises
                    the conceptual development of the book and online portal <hi rendition="#i"
                        >[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora.</hi> She previously directed the
                    Institute for the History of the German Jews in Hamburg, where she initiated and
                    ran the <hi rendition="#i">Key Documents</hi> project. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Translators</hi><lb/> Andreas Bredenfeld, Berlin<lb/> Jake
                    Schneider, Berlin <lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="team-book" n="2">
                <head>Book Publication Team</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Authors</hi><lb/> Prof. Michael Brenner<lb/> Dr. Sheer
                    Ganor (lead author and editor)<lb/> Prof. Marion A. Kaplan<lb/> Prof. 
                    Guy Miron<lb/> Prof. Miriam Rürup (lead author and editor)<lb/></p>

                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Editorial Team</hi><lb/> Dr. Lisa Sophie Gebhard (coordinator
                    and editor)<lb/> Verena Kurz<lb/> Paul-Levi Mydlach (editorial assistant)<lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Advisory Board</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> The content of the hybrid project benefits from the support and oversight of an
                    advisory board of distinguished international scholars, including experts from
                    the three countries where Leo Baeck Institutes have been located since 1955.
                    Many of the members also contributed to earlier volumes of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >German-Jewish History in the Modern Era</hi>. </p>
                <list>
                    <item> Prof. Ofer Ashkenazi – Director, Richard Koebner Minerva Center for
                        German History at Hebrew University of Jerusalem</item>
                    <item> Prof. Atina Grossmann – Professor of History at the Faculty of
                        Humanities and Social Sciences at Cooper Union in New York City </item>
                    <item> Prof. Dr. Simone Lässig – Director of the German Historical Institute in
                        Washington, DC </item>
                    <item> Prof. Jeffrey Lesser – Samuel Candler Dobbs Professor and Director of
                        the Halle Institute for Global Research and Learning, Emory University,
                        Atlanta </item>
                    <item> Prof. Michael A. Meyer – Adolph S. Ochs Professor of Jewish History
                        Emeritus at Hebrew Union College – Jewish Institute of Religion, Cincinnati </item>
                    <item> Prof. David Rechter – Professor of Modern Jewish History at the
                        Faculty of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies, University of Oxford </item>
                    <item> PD Katrin Steffen – DAAD Professor of European and Jewish History and
                        Culture at the University of Sussex </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Sponsor</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Since 2023, the <ref target="https://www.volkswagenstiftung.de/en"
                        >VolkswagenStiftung</ref> has been financing the hybrid publication project
                    of the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi>’s (LBI) Academic Working
                    Group, which is under the direction of Prof. Miriam Rürup at the Moses
                    Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies in Potsdam.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
