<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Overall project</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2023-09-06</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--
                <head>Overall project</head>
                <lb/>
            -->
            <div xml:id="overall-project" n="2">
                <p> The online portal '[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora' is part of a
                    hybrid publication project of the <hi rendition="#i"><ref
                            target="http://wag-leobaeck.de/">Academic Working Group</ref></hi> of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi> (WAG). The beginnings of this
                    project date back to 2015, when Michael Brenner, as international president of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi>, convened a workshop in
                    Washington D.C. There, Simone Lässig, Director of the <hi rendition="#i">German
                        Historical Institute</hi>, hosted a discussion on the continuation of the
                    book series on <hi rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi>.
                    This led to the idea of focusing on German-Jewish history outside Germany as a
                    new project of the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi>. Michael Brenner
                    and Miriam Rürup discussed these initial ideas in a <ref
                        target="https://badw.de/die-akademie/presse/videos/video-detail/detail/nachdenken-ueber-die-diaspora.html"
                        >Video of the ad hoc working group “Future Values” of the Bavarian Academy
                        of Sciences and Humanities</ref> (in German). </p>
                <p> Under the direction of Miriam Rürup, the project is being realized at the Moses
                    Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies (MMZ) in Potsdam since 2020 and
                    coordinated by Lisa Sophie Gebhard since 2023. The <hi rendition="#i"><ref
                            target="https://www.volkswagenstiftung.de/en/"
                        >VolkswagenStiftung</ref></hi> supports the research project with
                    third-party funding. The aim is to provide an overview of the German-Jewish
                    diaspora through a synthesis of previous research and new archival research. The
                    focus will be on the lives of German-speaking Jews after they fled or emigrated
                    from their countries of origin. As a hybrid project, this digital portal is
                    being created together with an anthology that will conclude the renowned series
                        <hi rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi> (C. H. Beck
                    Munich, 1996-2012). While the previous five volumes focused on Jewish life <hi
                        rendition="#i">within</hi> the German lands, this project aims to create a
                    reference work on German-Jewish history <hi rendition="#i">outside</hi> the
                    German-speaking world. The afterlife of German-speaking Jewry after the Shoah
                    will be taken into account. </p>
                <p> In conjunction with the print publication, the <ref target="./about/website"
                        >online portal</ref> offers the opportunity to present individual places,
                    historical figures and sources in more detail. At the same time, new entries can
                    be added as they become available. Through this hybrid approach, we aim to
                    create synergies and go beyond conventional thinking in terms of printed pages.
                    In the anthology, some of the portal contributions are linked to the book
                    chapters, so that both projects are interlinked and form a joint undertaking. </p>
                <p>The anthology is being written by the historians Michael Brenner, Sheer Ganor,
                    Marion A. Kaplan, Guy Miron and Miriam Rürup, with Sheer Ganor and Miriam Rürup
                    serving as the main authors and editors. The volume is expected to be published
                    in early 2027. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
