<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">German(speaking)-Jewish Diaspora – Introduction</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2025-05-08</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Few concepts have had as profound an impact on the Jewish experience of history as
                the word ‘diaspora’. Ever since the First Temple in Jerusalem was destroyed in the
                sixth century BCE, experiences of escape, expulsion, and displacement, lost homes,
                plural geographical affinities, and networks of international relationships have
                characterized Jewish history, religion, tradition, and imagination. Alongside
                migration, which is the prerequisite for any diasporic community, diaspora, from the
                Ancient Greek for ‘scattering’, lies at the heart of Jewish experience.</p>
            <p>The Diaspora portal focuses on historical themes through the lens of individual
                biographies and contemporary documents linked to Germanophone lifeworlds. The portal
                is not limited to Jews from Germany, however. More than questions of citizenship or
                nationality, the portal centers on a multifaceted cultural and linguistic community
                with shared German(speaking) heritage as a point of departure. Any attempt to pin
                down lifeworlds in conceptual terms risks narrowing the diversity of social practice
                as it is actually lived. The label ‘Jewish’ comes with its own problems, given that
                a number of the figures discussed here did not identify or define themselves as
                such. In some cases, they only became ‘Jews’ as a result of their persecution under
                the imposed classification of <hi rendition="#i">Jude</hi>.</p>
            <p>Within German-Jewish lifeworlds and historical experiences, the interpretation of
                that term, ‘German-Jewish’, is a core research question. Beginning in the era of the
                    <hi rendition="#i">Haskalah</hi>, the Jewish Enlightenment, and then with the
                nascent legal emancipation during the long nineteenth century, Jews debated their
                identities as Germans and/or Jews with their contemporaries. The two-pronged term
                ‘German-Jewish’ arose from that debate. Today, the term is employed less as a
                normative value statement than as a cultural descriptor – and could be rendered more
                accurately as ‘Germanophone-Jewish’. For the sake of both readability and continuity
                with previous scholarship, we nevertheless retain ‘German-Jewish’ in most instances.
                Still, the hyphenate is clunky – and we are well aware that readers will stumble
                over it. Through that hyphen, we aim to carve out space for nuance, multiple
                affiliations, transnationalism, and biographical open-endedness.</p>
            <p>The Diaspora portal adopts a broad geographical vantage point and endeavors to
                remember the heterogeneous group of German-speaking Jews whose roots stretch back
                not only to Germany, but also to Lithuania, Austria, Poland, Slovakia, Czechia,
                Hungary, and elsewhere. In these regions, the German language was often seen as a
                ‘language of upward mobility’ in the sense of <hi rendition="#i"
                    >embourgeoisement</hi>; the language itself frequently proved to be the most
                enduring marker of a migratory biography that remained visibly or audibly
                German-Jewish. In many cases, diasporic contexts only emerged by way of the longing
                for this linguistic homeland.</p>
            <div xml:id="what-does-diaspora-mean" n="2">
                <head>What Does Diaspora Mean?</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>‘Diaspora’ is both a descriptive term and a scholarly one. As an analytical
                    concept, it ideally captures the manifold, dynamic, and complex nature of
                    German-speaking Jews’ migrations and the processes by which they made themselves
                    at home. The word diaspora may be employed in two related ways. On the one hand,
                    it categorizes a set of individuals belonging to the same ethnic and/or religious
                    group who have been compelled to leave their country of origin yet maintain a
                    strong and lasting connection to its culture and heritage – sometimes for
                    multiple generations.</p>
                <p>On the other, diaspora also contains an inherent spatial imaginary: it designates
                    the experiential realms of such a set of individuals from a shared ethnic and/or
                    religious group who are living outside their original center, yet maintain an
                    attachment to that Old Country, which they were forced to leave under duress,
                    through traditions and memory. In both variants, diaspora presupposes the
                    migration and communal life of a group – held together by real or imagined
                    ties.</p>
                <p>According to Jewish tradition, <hi rendition="#i">Eretz Yisrael</hi> – the ‘Land
                    of Israel’ – is this symbolic center, which has long been the reference point of
                    religious practice and has assumed a new role since the founding of the State of
                    Israel. Diaspora is a dynamic and ever-evolving practice, but also a social and
                    symbolic space.</p>
                <p>The original Jewish understanding of diaspora, conveyed through the Hebrew terms
                        <hi rendition="#i">galut</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">tfutzot</hi> (exile,
                    dispersion) emerged after the expulsion from ancient Israel and was thus linked
                    to a continual longing for a return to <hi rendition="#i">Zion</hi>.</p>
                <p>On 14 May 1948, the founding of the State of Israel seemingly rendered a
                    conceptually meaningful Jewish diaspora obsolete. And yet, Jewish life continued
                    to exist beyond the new state’s borders. Even today, the majority of Jews live
                    in the United States, not Israel; hence, we must acknowledge the existence of at
                    least two geographic centers. Notwithstanding, the establishment of a (renewed)
                    territorial center with sovereign statehood in Israel raised the question of
                    whether this marked the end of the Jewish diaspora – long connoted negatively as
                        <hi rendition="#i">galut</hi> (exile).</p>
                <p>The ancient Greek concept of diaspora (διασπορά), roughly meaning ‘dispersion,’
                    is itself a product of Jewish diasporic communities. It first appears in the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Septuagint</hi> – the earliest Greek translation of the
                    Torah, which was created by Jewish scholars, mostly in Alexandria. At the time,
                    more than 2,200 years ago, the majority of Jews were already living outside <hi
                        rendition="#i">Eretz Yisrael</hi>, and the term did not yet hold the same
                    negative associations that would later cling to it. After the destruction of the
                    Second Temple in 70 CE and the subsequent expulsions of many Jews under the
                    Roman occupation, the term diaspora became widespread. It was given a negative
                    (religious) interpretation, foremost associated with expulsion, displacement,
                    enslavement, and coercion, with powerlessness and territorial homelessness.</p>
                <p>In the twentieth century, even before the founding of Israel, the Jewish meaning
                    of the term diaspora underwent a further transformation. The historian Simon
                    Dubnow (1860–1941), born in what is now Belarus, together with other Jewish
                    intellectuals in Eastern Europe, developed the notion of a ‘Diaspora
                    nationalism’ that consciously embraced a national project in the diaspora,
                    adding political agency to the concept and demonstrating that Jewish identity
                    can exist without a sovereign state as its center. In this context, diaspora was
                    no longer viewed merely as the result of dispersion, but also as a space of
                    cultural and social agency.</p>
                <p>The term diaspora has passed through a range of meanings in academic research,
                    including the fields of Jewish history and historiography. Since the 1980s, it
                    has seen a revival across disciplines, not only as a descriptive term but also
                    as an analytical category, after previously being understood primarily in a
                    religious and usually negative sense, as a condition of forced exile. Our
                    approach, too, seeks to move beyond <hi rendition="#i">galut</hi> and exile,
                    focusing instead on the concrete social practices and dynamic processes of group
                    formation among historical actors.</p>
                <p>The historian Steven M. Lowenstein (1945–2020), himself a New York-born child of
                    Jewish refugees from Germany, coined the phrase ‘German-Jewish diaspora’<note
                        type="editorial" place="foot">Steven M. Lowenstein, “Epilogue: The
                        German-Jewish Diaspora,” in: Michael A. Meyer (ed.), <hi rendition="#i"
                            >German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi>, vol. 4: Renewal and
                        Destruction, 1918–1945, New York: Columbia University Press, 1998, 393–402.
                        Published in German as “Epilog: Die deutsch-jüdische Diaspora,” in: Avraham
                        Barkai/Paul Mendes-Flohr, <hi rendition="#i">Deutsch-jüdische Geschichte
                            in der Neuzeit</hi>, edited by Michael A. Meyer, vol. 4, München: C.H. Beck, 2000, 372–381.</note>
                    for the communities that formed from 1933 onward. We have adopted his
                    articulation from the epilogue to the fourth volume of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi> (1997) as a systematic tool for
                    continuing that history in a dual sense.</p>
                <p>In doing so, we will first seek to broaden the exile-based understanding of
                    diaspora by examining how Jewish exiles developed a sort of diasporic
                    relationship to their German or German-speaking communities of origin. Second,
                    we will ponder the extent to which German/ophone-Jewish culture remained salient
                    for these individuals. Thus, we are also preoccupied with the collective
                    maintenance of a German-Jewish identity outside the German-speaking world. Other
                    Jewish groups, too, have developed a similar kind of dual diaspora, notably the
                    Sephardi Jews, whose community formation and continuing orientation toward the
                    expulsions from the Iberian Peninsula in 1492 from Spain and in 1496 from
                    Portugal are still reflected today in a shared language (Ladino) and in
                    religious customs.</p>
                <p>Scholarly discussions of diasporic minorities have proposed various definitions
                    for what constitutes a diasporic identity. Some of the common threads across
                    these definitions, albeit with differing emphases, include the following.</p>
                <p>A temporally well-defined starting point, typically associated with the expulsion
                    or forced displacement of large numbers of people or entire communities,
                    constitutes the origin of a diaspora. At the same time, the settlement of this
                    group outside the region of origin establishes a geographical point of
                    reference. These aspects are accompanied by efforts to preserve, or even create,
                    community-building practices in the country of exile – such as through
                    landsmanshaft-style organizations – alongside a continued, often tense
                    relationship with the new living environment and a continued emotional
                    attachment to the ‘lost homeland’. This attachment is often accompanied by a
                    vague longing for a past inflected by the Old Country, linked to hopes of
                    transcending the pain of expulsion – even if only in the imagination.</p>
                <p>This first overview of the German-Jewish <hi rendition="#i">diaspora</hi> draws
                    on existing research and new archival findings to investigate the historical
                    circumstances that led to German-Jewish migration, and the ways in which
                    Germanophone Jews sought to preserve their cultures of origin and affiliation(s)
                    in various countries of refuge – and to safeguard them as part of a
                    German-Jewish cultural heritage. Given the hybrid and often fragmented nature of
                    the resulting affiliations, we are particularly interested in the extent to
                    which this group developed shared identities in each ‘New Country’ – identities
                    shaped not only by distance, homesickness, and loss, but also by proximity,
                    arrival, and a sense of belonging.</p>
                <p>Such processes of group formation also bring into focus the relationship to the
                    majority society and to other minorities (including other Jewish groups). These
                    relationships were often riven by tensions, which in turn encouraged the
                    institutionalization of dedicated spaces, organizations, and representative
                    bodies. Alongside this group-specific multiplicity of cultural affiliation, the
                    analytical category of diaspora also makes it possible to trace transnational
                    networks. The relationships among German-speaking Jews, who viewed themselves as
                    part of a larger (imagined) intercontinental community, open up doors for an
                    additional, particularly rich field of analysis. This approach offers two
                    different avenues to a transnational turn in German-Jewish history, as it also
                    considers those who remained in the Old Country.</p>
                <p>We reflect afresh on the concept of diaspora in each region where significant
                    numbers of German-speaking Jews settled. A sense of self dominated by
                    reminiscences and ties to the Old Country did not always emerge. This project
                    also addresses processes of detachment and decoupling. It also examines
                    questions of return migration, including migration to one of the two postwar
                    German states. After the Second World War, no more than five percent of the
                    roughly 450,000 German-speaking Jews ever returned to their respective Old
                    Country. Nevertheless, numerous examples attest to how intensely those who had
                    emigrated wrestled with the possibility of returning to their countries of
                    origin, often for years. In some cases, they went through with it, temporarily
                    or on an exploratory basis.<note type="editorial" place="foot">Sheer Ganor, <hi
                            rendition="#i">Somewhere from Long Ago:</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">The Global Displacement of German-Speaking Jewry</hi>, 4
                        (forthcoming).</note></p>
                <p>Besides examining the political, societal, and social challenges that newcomers
                    encountered in each destination, this project also explores the opportunities
                    available to Germanophone Jews and the extent of their participation in the
                    mainstream societies around them. At the same time, we examine the emergence of
                    a widely dispersed German-Jewish diaspora and its transterritorial
                    connections.</p>
                <p>By adopting a transnational perspective that takes German-Jewish history outside
                    the German-speaking region as a premise, we bring new facets of Jewish
                    experience into view, and can disrupt the methodological fixation on the
                    nation-state. Understanding the German-Jewish diaspora, with all its
                    particularities, as inherently part of the global migration movements that
                    shaped the twentieth century – and continue to shape our present – also reveals
                    points of connection with <hi rendition="#i">Diaspora Studies</hi> and (Global)
                        <hi rendition="#i">Migration Studies</hi>.</p>
                <p>The topic of diaspora remains equally relevant today. Since the 7 October 2023
                    attack by the Hamas terrorist organization and the ensuing war in Gaza, many
                    Jews in the diaspora – including descendants of German-speaking refugees – have
                    been rethinking their Jewish identities with regard to both Israel and their
                    families’ Old Country. This project highlights the central role of migration and
                    diaspora in Jewish history and affirms their continuing relevance for current
                    developments. Growing antisemitism – which in the past was a major push factor
                    for migration – is now driving an increase in migration, alongside political
                    developments such as the rightward shift in Israeli politics and the war in
                    Ukraine. In 2024, the number of people globally who were forced to leave their
                    homes as a result of war, conflict, and persecution reached an all-time high.
                    Migration – often involuntary – is thus pervasive in our own present moment, and
                    new diasporic communities, both Jewish and non-Jewish, are emerging in its
                    wake.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="what-does-germanspeaking-jewish-mean" n="2">
                <head>What Does ‘German(speaking)-Jewish’ Mean?</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The term ‘German-Jewish’ calls to mind the idea of a cultural symbiosis in
                    Germany during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries – an idea that
                    was rattled by the Nazis’ taking power in 1933 and then obliterated by the
                    Shoah. The political theorist and philosopher Hannah Arendt (1906–1975)
                    addressed this problem in her biography <hi rendition="#i">Rahel Varnhagen</hi>
                    (1938/1957). Arendt described the notion of a ‘German-Jewish symbiosis’ as an
                    illusion, and showed how Jewish efforts at assimilation in the nineteenth
                    century ultimately failed in the face of persistent antisemitism. For Arendt,
                    only the shared language offered some form of cultural continuity. Many of the
                    individuals described on this portal did not view themselves primarily as
                    ‘Germans,’ but rather as part of a Central European, culturally diverse public
                    sphere. The term ‘Germanophone’ points to this intellectual breadth – between
                    Prague, Vienna, Breslau (Wrocław), and beyond.</p>
                <p>In the context of the diasporic lived realities documented by the Diaspora
                    portal, this is not so much a matter of the subjects’ identification with a
                    nationality or a sovereign state. After all, many future émigrés no longer
                    identified with such affiliations after the First World War, when the borders of
                    Central Europe were redrawn, or else distanced themselves from these newly
                    demarcated states following the Nazi rise to power in 1933 and the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Anschluss</hi> (annexation) of Austria in 1938. For many, the
                    German language was less a marker of national identity than a kind of cultural
                    homeland. In the diaspora, language, education, religion, and cultural practice
                    became key elements of identity, although personal experiences and perspectives
                    varied widely. For the first generation, at least, ‘German’ was often a fixture
                    of everyday life – in the family, at school, and in religious and cultural
                    contexts. In many cases, the language was passed down for generations.</p>
                <p>As seen from a bird’s-eye view, the German-speaking Jewish diaspora was
                    characterized by a diversity of biographical backgrounds, experiences of
                    migration, and self-described identifications. Cities of origin such as
                    Czernowitz (now Chernivtsi), Lemberg (now Lviv), Vienna, Prague, or Breslau (now
                    Wrocław) reveal that ‘German’ often signified a cultural rather than a national
                    belonging – a notion more accurately conveyed by the term ‘Germanophone’. Life
                    trajectories that moved between these places illustrate the intra-European
                    entanglements within this diverse community – for example, numerous binational
                    marriages, often among German speakers, but with sometimes pairing cultures
                    known in German as <hi rendition="#i">ostjüdisch</hi> (Eastern Jewish, i.e.,
                    historically Yiddish-speaking) and <hi rendition="#i">westjüdisch</hi> (i.e.,
                    Germanophone).</p>
                <p>German-speaking Jews in Mandatory Palestine and later Israel shared a distinct
                    experience. Many of them, especially those born and raised in Germany, found
                    refuge in Palestine from 1933 onward, bringing their language and culture with
                    them – as did all immigrant groups – and contributing to the local public
                    sphere. The German language often remained a central element of their identity,
                    although this went along with a particular shame given its status as the
                    ‘language of the perpetrators.’ Those German-speaking immigrants, nicknamed
                    ‘Yekkes,’ had in common their experiences of skepticism from other Jewish groups
                    – who often asked them whether they had moved there “out of Zionist conviction
                    or out of Germany.”</p>
                <p>When we use the phrase ‘Germanophone-Jewish’ or ‘German-speaking Jewish,’ then,
                    we aim to highlight the existence of linguistic-cultural affiliations beyond the
                    taxonomies of sovereign states. Language functioned as a cultural homeland, and
                    the hyphenate term <hi rendition="#i">Germanophone</hi>-Jewish reflects the
                    specific diasporic experience at the heart of this portal. That experience may
                    also be shared by descendants who neither speak the language nor personally
                    identify as Jewish.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="where-does-a-german-jewish-diaspora-emerge-spatial-scope" n="2">
                <head>Where Does a German-Jewish Diaspora Emerge? Spatial Scope</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Diaspora portal is devoted to the lifeworlds of German-speaking Jews who,
                    especially from 1933 onwards, built new lives in a range of countries, both
                    transit stops and longer-term destinations – spanning an ABC of destinations,
                    starting with Australia, Brazil, and Cyprus. The most important centers of the
                    German-Jewish diaspora, such as the United States and Palestine/Israel, have
                    already been the subject of extensive research as individual locations, often
                    showing their development over extended periods. More recently, lesser-known
                    destinations such as Kenya, Shanghai, the Caribbean, and the Philippines have
                    also been explored in insightful case studies. However, there has been no
                    comparative study to date of these highly diverse transit and destination
                    countries. With this Diaspora portal, we aim to shed light on the full
                    geographical scope of German-Jewish dispersion and to present a panorama of its
                    transnational entanglements. In addition to the ‘conventional’ destinations, in
                    which a German-speaking Jewish community successfully took root, we also take
                    into account ‘transit countries’ – including waystations such as Shanghai – and
                    the temporary diasporic structures that developed in such environments. Even in
                    these waystations, distinct forms of community emerged which continue to exist
                    in collective memory as a ‘remembered diaspora,’ even though the exiles
                    themselves have long resided elsewhere.</p>
                <p>The chief destinations for German-speaking Jews during the period of the Nazi
                    regime were the United States, the United Kingdom, and Mandatory Palestine. Of
                    the roughly one hundred countries in which these refugees found permanent or
                    temporary sanctuary, Argentina also held core significance. Around 75 percent of
                    German-speaking Jews settled in these four diasporic centers alone. After the
                    outbreak of the Second World War, opportunities to emigrate grew increasingly
                    scarce, and destinations such as Cuba, Shanghai, Turkey, and Iran became
                    life-saving havens.<note type="editorial" place="foot">Lowenstein, “Epilogue:
                        The German-Jewish Diaspora,” 372 in the German edition.</note></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#b">What About Israel?</hi></p>
                <p>In addition to the three major centers – the US, the UK, and Argentina – we also
                    consider Palestine/Israel. Between 1933 and 1945, no territory received as many
                    immigrants from the German-speaking world, relative to the total population, as
                    did Palestine under the British Mandate. This differed fundamentally from all
                    other countries of immigration in that migration to <hi rendition="#i">Eretz
                        Yisrael</hi>, according to Jewish tradition, was interpreted as an act of
                    returning. Thus, the concept of diaspora cannot be readily applied to Israel
                    without qualification. Nevertheless, the great hardships on the ground and the
                    loss of a previous life in Europe – which even most Zionists would not have
                    willingly given up for a life in <hi rendition="#i">Eretz Israel</hi> – left
                    many Germanophone Jews with feelings of alienation and difference. Tellingly, it
                    was within a society dominated by Zionism – which exerted particularly strong
                    pressure on newcomers to assimilate – that a pronounced sense of regional
                    solidarity emerged, often anchored in a sense of a shared German-Jewish
                    origin.</p>
                <p>With the establishment of the State of Israel in 1948, the imagined homeland –
                    which before had only manifested in Heinrich Heine’s (1797–1856) image of the
                    Torah as a portable ‘fatherland’ – became a real-existing sovereign state for
                    Jews. As a result, the concept of diaspora underwent a Zionization process that
                    remains a subject of lively debate among Jews. Proponents of the Zionist
                    worldview spoke of an end to the diaspora condition – and in some cases,
                    questioned the very legitimacy of Jewish life outside Israel. Non-Zionist voices
                    countered this with the argument that an affirmative embrace of the diaspora
                    condition could have world-historical significance. Jewish understandings of
                    diaspora itself diversified in reaction to its supposed conclusion via the
                    ‘return to the homeland’ constituted by the establishment of statehood.</p>
                <p>German Jews, known in Israel as ‘Yekkes’ to this day, left significant lasting
                    marks on the Jewish society of Mandatory Palestine from the early twentieth
                    century onward. Major centers of their migration included the port city of
                    Haifa, the northern town of Nahariya, and the Jerusalem neighborhood of Rehavia
                    – each of which has been the subject of dedicated research. German-Jewish
                    influence made itself felt in Tel Aviv, too, perhaps most visibly in the
                    migration of architecture: the <hi rendition="#i">Bauhaus</hi> style.<note
                        type="editorial" place="foot"> For the case of Haifa, the comprehensive
                        volume edited by Anja Siegemund, <hi rendition="#i">Deutsche und
                            zentraleuropäische Juden in Palästina und Israel.</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Kulturtransfer, Lebenswelten, Identitäten. Beispiele aus
                            Haifa</hi> (Berlin: Neofelis, 2016). For Nahariya, see Klaus Kreppel,
                            <hi rendition="#i">Nahariyya und die deutsche Einwanderung nach Eretz
                            Israel: Die Geschichte seiner Einwohner von 1935 bis 1941</hi> (Tefen:
                        Das Offene Museum, 2010), and <hi rendition="#i">Nahariyya – das Dorf der
                            “Jeckes”: Die Gründung der Mittelstandssiedlung für deutsche Einwanderer
                            in Eretz Israel 1934/1935</hi> (Tefen: Das Offene Museum, 2005). For
                        Rehavia, see most recently Thomas Sparr, <hi rendition="#i">Grunewald im
                            Orient: Das deutsch-jüdische Jerusalem</hi>, 2nd ed. (Berlin: Berenberg,
                        2018) and Christian Kraft, <hi rendition="#i">Aschkenas in Jerusalem: Die
                            religiösen Institutionen der Einwanderer aus Deutschland im Jerusalemer
                            Stadtviertel Rechavia (1933–2004) – Transfer und Transformation</hi>
                        (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2014). On the history of Tel Aviv,
                        and beyond, see research by Joachim Schlör and Ita Heinze-Greenberg, among
                        others.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="when-did-the-germanophone-jewish-diaspora-begin-temporal-scope" n="2">
                <head>When Did the Germanophone Jewish Diaspora Begin? Temporal Scope</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Diaspora portal strives to paint a holistic picture of the various historical
                    phases of German-Jewish migration, so as to lend visibility to the historical
                    points of departure, continuities, and ruptures of the German-Jewish diaspora
                    over an extended period.</p>
                <p>A larger number of Jews from Germany began migrating to other countries as early
                    as the 1830s – long before the Nazi seizure of power – primarily to North
                    America. In addition, most of the more than two million Jews who emigrated from
                    Eastern Europe to the United States between 1881 and the 1920s also traveled via
                    Germany as a transit country. As a result, the United States had become the most
                    important center of Jewish life outside Europe by around 1900. New German-Jewish
                    immigrants already made up a significant proportion of Jewish communities in
                    many places during the nineteenth century.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#b">Exile and Emigration: 1933–1945</hi></p>
                <p>Starting in 1933, the German-Jewish diaspora ballooned to a never before seen
                    dimension. After control of Germany was transferred to the Nazi Party, between
                    250,000 and 300,000 German Jews managed to emigrate – often after losing their
                    possessions, enduring long waits, and passing through assorted European transit
                    points. A further 150,000 or so German-speaking Jews followed suit in the wake
                    of the ‘Anschluss’ of Austria and the German occupation of Czechoslovakia in
                    1938, amidst the growing radicalization of Nazi policies of persecution and
                    forced expulsion.</p>
                <p>After the war began in September 1939, emigration became increasingly difficult.
                    Many Jews were caught up in the fighting in the countries where they had sought
                    a safe haven; in October 1941, the Nazis finally outlawed all emigration.</p>
                <p>Between 1933 and 1941, around 400,000 to 430,000 Germanophone Jews were forced to
                    leave their Central European Old Countries due to growing antisemitic
                    discrimination and persecution. There is still no way of precisely calculating
                    the total number of women, children, and men who were forced to escape the
                    countries and regions where they were raised. Estimates suggest that in addition
                    to the 270,000 to 300,000 Jews from Germany, roughly 130,000 came from Austria
                    and around 25,000 from the ‘Sudetenland’ and the Protectorate of Bohemia and
                    Moravia, now in the Czech Republic.<note type="editorial" place="foot">Sheer
                        Ganor, <hi rendition="#i">Somewhere from Long Ago</hi>, 4.</note> In all of
                    these regions, they were unprotected and at the mercy of Nazi tyranny, which
                    came to an end in May 1945 with the unconditional surrender of the
                    Wehrmacht.</p>
                <p>The role of the Nazi period as a turning point in Jewish history is a visible
                    focus of the Diaspora portal, but we do not restrict the project to the period
                    of Nazi rule. Where it is historically accurate and supported by sources and
                    research, we also examine German-Jewish lifeworlds beyond the German-speaking
                    world both before 1933 and after 1945. In doing so, we seek to make productive
                    use of and draw insights from the intergenerational possibilities of diaspora by
                    considering multiple generations in their respective historical developments and
                    interconnections.</p>
                <p>This broader time frame cannot be applied equally to all countries. Nevertheless,
                    we also include places where no German-speaking Jewish community had taken root
                    before 1933 and where no lasting one developed afterwards. In order to document
                    the German-Jewish diaspora – which was shaped in many cases by transmigration,
                    as a transnational history of entanglements and relationships across time and
                    space – we also make a point of including diasporic structures that were
                    short-lived.</p>
                <p>Miriam Rürup, Lisa Sophie Gebhard</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="further-introductory-reading" n="3">
                <head>Further Introductory Reading</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> Liliana Ruth Feierstein, “Diaspora,” in: Christina von Braun/Micha Brumlik
                    (eds.), <hi rendition="#i">Handbuch Jüdische Studien</hi>, Wien/Köln/Weimar:
                    Böhlau, 2017, 99–109. </p>
                <p> Sheer Ganor, <hi rendition="#i">Somewhere from Long Ago: The Global Displacement
                        of German-Speaking Jewry</hi> (forthcoming). </p>
                <p> Grit Jilek, <hi rendition="#i">Nation ohne Territorium. Über die Organisierung
                        der jüdischen Diaspora bei Simon Dubnow</hi>, Baden-Baden: Nomos, 2013. </p>
                <p> Marion Kaplan, “Did German Jews Remain German Jews Once They Left Their
                    Homeland?,” in: Hasia R. Diner (ed.), <hi rendition="#i">The Oxford Handbook of
                        the Jewish Diaspora</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2021, 431–455. </p>
                <p> Steven M. Lowenstein, “Epilogue: The German-Jewish Diaspora,” in: Michael A.
                    Meyer (ed.), <hi rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in Modern Times</hi>, vol.
                    4: Renewal and Destruction, 1918–1945, New York: Columbia University Press,
                    1998, 393–402.</p>
                <p> Miriam Rürup (ed.), <hi rendition="#i">Praktiken der Differenz. Diasporakulturen
                        in der Zeitgeschichte</hi>, Göttingen: Wallstein 2009. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
