<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Editorial Model and Guidelines</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2025-05-05</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="redaktionsmodell" n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Editorial Model</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Diaspora Portal is an international and interdisciplinary collaborative
                    effort. The Moses Mendelssohn Center in Potsdam is responsible for the editorial
                    oversight and coordination as well as the technical implementation. However, the
                    project is largely co-created by the currently more than 100 authors of
                    contributions in various genres. They come from more than 20 countries, with
                    journalists, writers and academics contributing case studies. In the long term,
                    the Diaspora Portal is also intended to become a place for international,
                    interdisciplinary and collaborative networking. Imagined as a 'Diaspora Tree',
                    we want to bring together different memory institutions in the respective
                    countries of immigration in order to make their work and collections visible and
                    to link them with each other in a targeted way.</p>
                <p>The authors of the country surveys work with the editors to review the
                    biographies and source presentations to be included in their country section.
                    The guidelines were discussed and debated at several digital kick-off meetings,
                    which also served as networking events.</p>
                <p> In addition to this two-stage review process, external reviewers were also asked
                    to review individual articles, depending on their expertise. This multi-stage
                    review process and the close collaboration between editors and authors ensure
                    the high quality of all contributions.</p>
                <p>The editorial team at the MMZ is responsible for coordinating the project. It
                    also checks the legal aspects of the publications and monitors the entire
                    process.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="editorial-guidelines" n="2">
                <head>Editorial Guidelines</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The various text genres of this portal follow a standardized scheme: A brief
                    summary at the beginning lists the most important aspects of a country, person
                    or source in relation to the German-Jewish diaspora. In all texts, names of
                    persons and organizations as well as place names are linked to standard data
                    records. This creates a comprehensive index both within the portal and links to
                    other digital projects. Metadata records have been created for all sources. We
                    also provide a transcription for sources reproduced as digital facsimiles and a
                    translation of the respective source for foreign-language texts. This makes it
                    easier to read handwritten texts, for example, and also makes the sources
                    searchable.</p>
                <p>Metadata records have been created for the XML transcripts in the online version,
                    and all historical documents are provided with metadata.</p>
                <p><!--Zur Erklärung von möglicherweise unbekannten Begriffen oder erwähnten Organisationen
                    entsteht zukünftig ein fortlaufend ergänztes Glossar.--> In
                    addition, all texts offer a small selected bibliography and further resources at
                    the end. The latter include links to other digital content (articles, online
                    exhibitions, digital copies, podcasts, films, etc.).</p>
                <p>The transcriptions were created by the editorial team as faithfully as possible
                    to the original. This includes preserving most of the original punctuation and
                    spelling. Spelling mistakes and abbreviations have been corrected. Any
                    ambiguities are explained in the notes. Emphasis and deletions are left visible,
                    especially if they have a substantive meaning.</p>
                <p> The original language of the country surveys, biographies, and source
                    interpretations is German or English. In the case of English-language
                    contributions, we have followed the spelling of the respective authors (American
                    or British English).</p>
                <p>Both the user interface and the content of the portal are intended to be
                    bilingual (English and German) throughout. Translations that are currently
                    missing are being worked on and will be added gradually.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
