<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Overall project</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Zentrum für
                        europäisch-jüdische Studien</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2023-09-06</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--
                <head>Overall project</head>
                <lb/>
            -->
            <div xml:id="overall-project" n="2">
                <p> The online portal ‘[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora’ is part of a
                    hybrid publication project of the <hi rendition="#i"><ref
                        target="http://wag-leobaeck.de/">Academic Working Group</ref></hi> (link in German) of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi> (LBI). This project’s origins
                    trace back to 2015, when Michael Brenner, then president of the international
                    LBI, invited scholars to a workshop in Washington, DC, hosted by Simone Lässig,
                    director of the city’s <hi rendition="#i">German Historical Institute</hi>, with
                    the aim of discussing a successor project to the German-, English- and
                    Hebrew-language book series <hi rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in Modern
                        Times</hi>. The workshop gave rise to the idea of creating a new LBI project
                    focused on German-Jewish history <hi rendition="#i">outside</hi> Germany’s
                    borders. Michael Brenner and Miriam Rürup discussed the initial conceptual
                    framework in a <ref
                        target="https://badw.de/die-akademie/presse/videos/video-detail/detail/nachdenken-ueber-die-diaspora.html"
                        >video by the ad-hoc “Values for the Future” working group at the Bavarian
                        Academy of Sciences and Humanities</ref> (in German). </p>
                <p> The project has been in the implementation phase since 2020, at the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies</hi>
                    (MMZ) in Potsdam, Germany with Miriam Rürup as principal investigator; Lisa
                    Sophie Gebhard has served as the project coordinator since 2023. The project is
                    financed by third-party funding from the <hi rendition="#i"><ref
                            target="https://www.volkswagenstiftung.de/en/"
                        >VolkswagenStiftung</ref></hi>. By synthesizing previous research in tandem
                    with new archival investigations, the initiative sets out to present an overview
                    of the German-Jewish diaspora that centers the lived experiences of
                    German-speaking Jews after they emigrated from or escaped their countries of
                    origin. In this hybrid project, the digital compendium accompanies an edited
                    anthology that will serve as the concluding volume of the distinguished book
                    series <hi rendition="#i">Deutsch-jüdische Geschichte in der Neuzeit</hi> (C. H.
                    Beck München, ongoing since 1996). Unlike the five preceding volumes, which were
                    thematically focused on Jewish life <hi rendition="#i">within</hi>
                    German-speaking countries, this book is intended as a foundational text for the
                    study of German-Jewish history <hi rendition="#i">outside</hi> these regions of
                    Europe. Thus, it examines the lifeworlds of German-speaking Jewry after the
                    Shoah. </p>
                <p> In conjunction with the printed edition, the <ref target="./about/website"
                        >digital platform</ref> allows the project to introduce individual
                    locations, historical individuals, and relevant sources in greater depth. The
                    format also allows for the publication of additional articles over time. By
                    pursuing this hybrid approach, we deliberately seek to create synergies and
                    transcend conventional thinking as manifested on the printed page. The anthology
                    will incorporate hyperlinks, pairing individual articles from the online
                    compendium with specific book chapters and thus intertwining the two projects
                    into a common initiative. </p>
                <p>The anthology will include essays by the historians Michael Brenner, Sheer Ganor,
                    Marion A. Kaplan, Guy Miron, and Miriam Rürup, with Sheer Ganor and Miriam Rürup
                    serving as lead authors and editors. The volume is slated to be published in
                    early 2027. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
