<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.rng"
type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="dtabf">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">About us</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/2130670-9">Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                        European-Jewish Studies</orgName>
                    <email>diaspora@juedische-geschichte-online.net</email>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Am Neuen Markt 8, 14467 Potsdam</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Potsdam</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">2025-05-08</date>
                <!--
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
                        <p>Dieser Text unterliegt den Bedingungen der Creative Commons Namensnennung
                            - Nicht kommerziell - Keine Bearbeitungen 4.0 International Lizenz.
                            Unter Namensnenung gemäß dem Zitationshinweis darf er in unveränderter
                            Form für nicht-kommerzielle Zwecke nachgenutzt werden.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p> The online portal ‘[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora’ is published by the
                Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish Studies (MMZ) in Potsdam and supervised
                by the project team there. It is part of the collaborative portal on European-Jewish
                history ‘<ref target="https://portal.jewish-history-online.net/">Jewish History
                    online</ref>’ hosted at the MMZ, and complements the Leo Baeck Institute’s
                anthology in the book series on ‘Modern German-Jewish History,’ which is expected to
                be published in early 2027. </p>
            <div xml:id="team-portal" n="2">
                <head>Portal Team</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Daniel Burckhardt, M.A. (Technical Implementation)</hi><lb/>
                    <lb/> has been a Research Associate at the Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                    European-Jewish Studies in Potsdam since 2021, where he is responsible for the
                    technical implementation of the online source portal ‘[Hi]stories of the
                    German-Jewish Diaspora’ among other tasks. Previously, he was the technical
                    developer for the “Key Documents on German-Jewish History” at the Institute for
                    the History of German Jews (IGdJ). He studied in Zurich and Berlin and worked as
                    a Research Associate at the Institute for the Historical Sciences, Humboldt
                    University in Berlin, at the Leibniz Centre for Contemporary History in Potsdam
                    (ZZF), and at the German Historical Institute in Washington, D.C. He also serves
                    on the editorial board and steering committee of H-Soz-Kult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Dr. Lisa Sophie Gebhard (Coordination and Editor)</hi>
                    <lb/> is a historian and Research Associate at the Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                    European-Jewish Studies in Potsdam, where she coordinates the international
                    publication project ‘[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora.’ She studied in
                    Berlin, Jerusalem, Kiel and Milan and received her doctorate from the Free
                    University of Berlin in 2022. Her dissertation, which focuses on the
                    multifaceted lifework of Davis Trietsch, an early Zionist, was funded by the
                    Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes and published in the Schriftenreihe
                    wissenschaftlicher Abhandlungen des Leo Baeck Instituts. Prior to joining the
                    MMZ she worked at the WZB Berlin Social Science Center, the German Historical
                    Museum, and Hentrich&amp;Hentrich Verlag für jüdische Kultur und Zeitgeschichte.
                    She lives with her family in Berlin. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Verena Kurz, M.A. (Editor)</hi>
                    <lb/> has been an external research assistant in the publication project
                    ‘[Hi]stories of the German-Jewish Diaspora’ at the Moses Mendelssohn Center for
                    European-Jewish Studies in Potsdam since 2024. She studied Cultural Studies,
                    Spanish Philology and Latin American Studies in Potsdam and Berlin. Study and
                    research stays, supported by DAAD scholarships, took her to Argentina, Bolivia
                    and Spain. In Buenos Aires, she headed the Liaison Office of the University of
                    Potsdam and worked in a historical archive to document the ‘anti-fascist’
                    founding history of the Pestalozzi School. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Paul-Levi Mydlach (Editorial Assistant)</hi><lb/> is a
                    student assistant at the Moses Mendelssohn Center in Potsdam. He is studying
                    history and German studies at the University of Potsdam, specializing in
                    German-Jewish history and literature.<lb/>
                </p>

                <p><hi rendition="#b">Prof. Dr. Miriam Rürup (Project Leader)</hi>
                    <lb/> has been Director of the Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish
                    Studies in Potsdam since 2020. As Head of the <hi rendition="#i">Academic
                        Working Group of the Leo Baeck Institute in Germany</hi> (WAG), she leads
                    the conceptual design of the book project and online portal “[Hi]stories of the
                    German-Jewish Diaspora.” She was previously Director of the Institute for the
                    History of German Jews in Hamburg, where she was the initiator and conceptual
                    editor and project manager of the so-called Key Documents Edition. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Translators</hi><lb/> Andreas Bredenfeld, Berlin<lb/> Jake
                    Schneider, Berlin <lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="team-book" n="2">
                <head>Book Publication Team</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Authors</hi><lb/> Prof. Dr. Michael Brenner<lb/> Dr. Sheer
                    Ganor (main author and editor)<lb/> Prof. Dr. Marion A. Kaplan<lb/> Prof. Dr.
                    Guy Miron<lb/> Prof. Dr. Miriam Rürup (main author and editor)<lb/></p>

                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Editors</hi><lb/> Dr. Lisa Sophie Gebhard (Coordination and
                    Editor)<lb/> Verena Kurz<lb/> Paul-Levi Mydlach (Editorial Assistant)<lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Advisory Board</head>
                <lb/>
                <p> This hybrid project also receives substantive support from a renowned,
                    international advisory board. It includes academics from the three countries in
                    which the <hi rendition="#i">Leo Baeck Institute</hi> has been located since
                    1955, some of whom also contributed to the predecessor volumes <hi
                        rendition="#i">German-Jewish History in the Modern Era</hi>. </p>
                <list>
                    <item> Prof. Ofer Ashkenazi, PhD, Director of the Koebner Minerva Research
                        Center for German History at Hebrew University of Jerusalem </item>
                    <item> Prof. Atina Grossmann, PhD, Professor of History in the Faculty of
                        Humanities and Social Sciences at the Cooper Union in New York City </item>
                    <item> Prof. Dr. Simone Lässig, Director of the German Historical Institute in
                        Washington, DC </item>
                    <item> Prof. Jeffrey Lesser, PhD, Samuel Candler Dobbs Professor and Director of
                        the Halle Institute for Global Research and Learning at Emory University,
                        Atlanta </item>
                    <item> Prof. Michael A. Meyer, PhD, Adolph S. Ochs Professor of Jewish History
                        Emeritus at the Hebrew Union College – Jewish Institute of Religion in
                        Cincinnati, Ohio </item>
                    <item> Prof. David Rechter, PhD, Professor of Modern Jewish History in the
                        Faculty of Asian and Middle Eastern Studies, University of Oxford </item>
                    <item> PD Dr. Katrin Steffen, DAAD Professor of European and Jewish History and
                        Culture at the University of Sussex </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
                <head>Sponsor</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Since 2023, the <ref target="https://www.volkswagenstiftung.de/en"
                        >VolkswagenStiftung</ref> has been funding the realization of the hybrid
                    publication project of the <hi rendition="#i">Academic Working Group of the Leo
                        Baeck Institute in Germany</hi> (WAG) under the leadership of its chair
                    Prof. Dr. Miriam Rürup at the Moses Mendelssohn Center for European-Jewish
                    Studies in Potsdam. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
